# MICHAEL LAFFERTY

Bioinformatics | Multi-omic Data Analysis

### CONTACT

(248) 840-1585

<u>Lafferty.Michael@gmail.com</u>

Website | LinkedIn | GitHub

Boston, MA

# **EDUCATION**

**PhD Bioinformatics and Computational Biology**University of North Carolina
Chapel Hill, NC, 2022

**BSE Chemical Engineering** University of Michigan Ann Arbor, MI, 2010

#### **LANGUAGES**

Python | R | Bash | Java | C++

#### **SKILLS**

Single-cell sequence analysis
Dimensionality reduction
Linear modeling
Data normalization
Gene ontology analysis
Gene set enrichment analysis
Colocalization analysis
Enrichment analysis

## **TOOLS**

PLINK | Seurat | STAR | Bowtie Salmon | Picard | Granges DESeq2 | matrixEQTL EMMAX | Gviz | GSEA

### **PROFILE**

I am a PhD in Bioinformatics and Computational Biology with over 13 years of industry and academic experience working in both dry-lab and wet-lab settings. I have a track record of rigorous science, bioinformatic expertise, and clear and concise communication. I love working on complex problems in a fast-paced and collaborative environment.

# **EXPERIENCE**

**BIOINFORMATICIAN**, Apr 2023 – Present **WATERSHED BIO**, Cambridge, MA

- Develop data analysis workflows and pipelines using python, R, and distributed computing environments
- Provide consultation on multi-omic data analysis (RNA-seq, Single-Cell RNA-seq, WGS, GWAS)
- Integrate public databases to enable customized target identification (UK Biobank, ChEMBL, OpenTargets, GTEx)

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCH ASSOCIATE, May2022 – Mar2023 GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT, May 2017 – May 2022 UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA, Chapel Hill, NC

- Investigated the role of genetic variation on gene expression in the developing human neocortex (mRNA/miRNA eQTLs)
- Implicated genes and genetic regulatory elements as possible mechanisms for developmental neuropsychiatric disorders via GWAS colocalizations
- Assessed reproducibility of human cortical organoid differentiations using single-cell rna-sequencing
- Developed data analysis pipelines for:
  - o Next generation sequencing (RNA-seq, ATAC-seq)
  - o Gene expression data (microarrays, differential gene expression)
  - o Genotyping and imputation analyses (1000 Genomes/TOPMed)
- Investigated biological pathways associated with neuronal proliferation and differentiation using human primary neural progenitor cells:
  - o Primary cell culture
  - o RNA extraction and quantification
  - o Immunocytochemistry and image analysis

**PROCESS DEVELOPMENT ASSOCIATE**, Jun 2015 – Jan 2016 **KBI BIOPHARMA**, Research Triangle Park, NC

 Developed unit operations for purification of novel biopharmaceuticals and scaled development purification processes for transfer to manufacturing